I'm going to introduce Élika
Élika, an assistant professor
at the University of Colorado Boulder.
Do you want to introduce me?
I will introduce you.
I'm so trying to get the slides going.
And Alex is a associate professor
in the Spanish department
at the University of California, Berkeley.
There you go.
So, a board member at the ELO.
So, woohoo!
Correct? Yes.
So I think we're going to be a little bit
out of step with the other papers
because we were supposed to be
in a different track,
but then there was an opening.
So here we are taking advantage of
a little bit extra time and seeing this.
Very cool projects.
So I'll begin reading this paper
that we prepared together.
A few months ago,
we were invited to read a chapter
on digital poetry for a
handbook on digital and American Studies.
We accepted, but to be frank, we weren't
sure how to write it in a way that hasn't
already been explored by the luminaries
who have extensively written on the topic.
So after debating some options
and modeling and the reference general
Intel by the handbook format,
we decided to take the opportunity
to examine our scholarly positionality
regarding randomness
and the media specificity
of reading in 2026.
The following is a joint reading
of selected fragments from said paper.
By reading directly from our text,
we hope to showcase
both our methodological approach
to collaborate.
Writing in the age of AI,
as well as our main intellectual
contributions to the topic of Latin
American digital poetry.
Let's begin.
What Latin American
digital poetry is depends on
who and what you ask,
or what you prompt the model to tell you.
First, you had to figure out
what you understand by Latin America.
Is the region simply
the geographical space delineated in
countless ways by the Spanish
and Portuguese colonial enterprises
in the in the 15th century?
Is it the individual countries
with the specific yet
connected and analogous histories?
Or is it rather
the that this world is always really hard?
The territorial diasporic space,
shaped by migrants
with roots in the geographic area
spread around the world.
How about the digital infrastructure
that follows colonial trade routes, and
thus continues to connect Latin American
peripherally with the rest of the world?
Uncertain about this complicated
geopolitical questions?
To pivot to the seemingly easier question
of what digital poetry
or digital poetics is done, most medium
specific strategies of meaning making
elite yield a poetic rather than outline
a literary genre like poetry.
Too complicated too.
Perhaps it's easier to start
with a third consideration
regarding the right terminology
to address your subject
of study
electronic poetry or digital poetry.
Are you talking about
the theory of digital poetry
or the historical interpretations
of what it works?
Or are you analyzing the works themselves?
Poetry or poetics?
Poetic works or poems?
Since you are tasked
to write a chapter on this question,
a handbook entry with its own general
conventions, you wonder how is it possible
to say something referential yet
new and insightful about an issue
that is simultaneously
very well studied and always
developing along and in response
to technological development?
So you find yourself discussing all this
with your colleague, and together
you set out to investigate these matters
from an uncomfortable position, one
that you hope can illuminate
the tensions of writing in early 2026,
you get together to write over zoom
on a shared Google document
activating myriad of digital
writing environment,
most of which you consider to be color,
others the one that make you
a little uncomfortable.
The automatic text extrusion machines,
chatbots, LLMs, rags are largely suspect,
but poking at them
may just let you address your original
task of surveying
Latin American digital poetry
as you investigate the formation
and distortions of the field
at a specific technical, cultural time
that equally shapes and situates
the media specificity of scholarship
itself.
I mean, why not?
Literature has always
been materialized
and concrete by digital writing tools,
and you believe you can use those way
to available to you these days
to examine how they interface
with your research topic a reflection,
a log, a synthesis,
the aura of second person personalization.
You soon realize that approach,
that approaching wedding in this way
opens up a number of significant tangents
that you can possibly address in detail
in these short pages, even though
you consider them to be indispensable
contexts, then questionable environmental
change, the attacks against democracy,
the deployment of LLMs against education
and critical thinking,
the textbook ellipse,
all of which you know to well,
get accentuated in the material realities
of Latin America.
You hope your readers or patient
with your choices reading this text
that while engaging synthetic texts,
you're trying really hard
not to make a gimmick of,
nor make your work easier or faster.
Probably not. Even better.
You hope it's speculative at best,
but if not at least exploratory.
You are not sure of your success
in this task, but you do hope your little
reading exercise will bring reader's
attention to the intermingling
of reading technologies
and poetics at this time.
Because if the question seems important
for the sake of writing an essay
on digital poetics,
imagine how relevant it should be
when conceptualizing
digital poetry itself.
And with this preliminary,
settled sort of,
you and your human colleague begin
working on Latin American digital poetry.
You know,
this feel like the back of your hand.
So coming up with a list of most relevant
critical works is not hard.
You complete the list with Gemini's
generated answer, wondering what that
LLM may have to offer
from its training data
and its current life
search functionalities.
You parse through those results,
noticing your human brain
missed 1 or 2 of Claudia [?]’s
numerous articles, real ones.
You check and you then drop all these
sources into Google's NotebookLM.
Keeping in mind that most of these sources
have already been incorporated into LLM’s
training data, and that NotebookLM
does not use user
input sources to train its core models.
User data remains private and separate
from model training, or so
you're being told.
The end result is a list including works
by Claudia Cossa,
Carolina Gainza, Thea
Bittman, Eduardo [?], Scott
Weintraub, [?] Diaz, and yourself,
among others.
You include the list
at the end of the chapter,
and you also reflect on the many choices
you are making here.
You expect that using this retrieval
and generative tools,
tools can reveal the themes,
strokes, and motifs in the scholarship
you already know
and need to be part of a reference.
To go like this, you also feel confident
that you can wear any incorrect
or inconsistent statements
based on your years of academic training.
After all, your human brains
and your human eyes have already read
all the sources,
but remain open to exploring.
What new can we even talk about that
adjective anymore anyway?
What new ideas might result
from the process?
It's unlikely that this will come from
the machine itself, but you'll find solace
in writing together with your colleague
to something good can come out of this.
You hope,
and you begin
with a critical positioning towards
Latin America.
You can't help but think of your proximity
and distance to Latin America.
You are both writing from the US.
Élika is from Mexico but hasn't
lived there for almost half her life.
Alex is from Spain,
but for the past 20 years has been living
in the mid-sized Latin American country
known as California,
whose population includes
approximately 16 million Latinos.
Considering this bit of personal history,
you might discuss how to approach
their theorization from your sources,
from your own positions,
both to scholars of Latin America
as scholars working and writing
from the United States, and as callers
thinking about literature produced via
digital technologies, you also addressed
the inherent political tensions of working
within your chosen writing environments.
Google's commercial products license
to universities, which deploy and exercise
power globally
but come from the particular local region
very close to Alex’s
As many of the authors from your sources
list note, there is a global local
friction between digital environments
and objects that is characteristic
of Latin American and digital poetry.
But is it truly distinctive?
Do you see this play in other regions?
Still?
Is this more unintentional positioning
stemming from the histories of line
above rather than a given location?
This is brought to
the forefront of your work once again.
With that, you ask and question each other
and eventually prompt
NotebookLM and Gemini around
two main issues how to define or delimit
Latin America
in the context of digital poetry,
and what is digital poetry
as defined by your chosen scholarship?
Addressing
the particularities of Latin America.
You read through these answers and discuss
among yourselves
as you check and query
for mistakes, inaccuracies, and whatnot.
And eventually you prune
the models answers and your human brains
synthesize them.
As current scholarship redefines
Latin America
not merely as a geographic territory,
but as a techno political zone.
It is a diasporic and linguistic network
that transcends national borders, united
by a shared condition of technological
and evidence, and a commitment
to resisting the digital
hegemony of the Global North.
Then we have a section in the slide
on positionality and identity
that we left out for timekeeping purposes.
What is digital poetry?
You have a similar slippery experience
when trying to get a definition
of digital poetry that you have decided
to leave out of this yellow presentation,
because you are confident your audience
will be familiar with the topic.
But do know that in the paper,
we reach a very interesting conclusion
about digital literature and its attention
to form, meaning and language,
playfully proposing
what may be the digital
is the poetics of digital literature,
and thus describing digital poetry
may be more expensive
than what you originally thought could be.
Could a medium be a poetic?
You decide to end this chapter
by bringing together
you two initial prompts
lend America and digital poetry,
and perhaps in an obvious fashion,
try to answer by going back in time.
After all, when defining digital poetry,
the but did talk to you about European
avant garde as possible as a possible
origin story, and you had to decide
to leave it out for being, well,
too Eurocentric.
But you back.
But you go back to your original notebook
about Latin American digital literature
and ask again.
Again, the following section problem.
I think the Western canon
has been removed from this presentation
for timekeeping purpose.
You realize that the more you focus on
the present, on the future of the general,
the further back
you need to go stretching yourself
beyond your original constraints.
You also realize that as it happens
with most things digital,
despite much work,
there's still a lack of handles
or parameters or traditions or conventions
to talk about
just poetry, but you decide not to worry
too much about it.
For now.
You actually like that.
Poetry seems to encompass anything poetic,
and you're going along with that.
After a while,
you realize that the word experimental
hasn't shown up at all,
even though it joins the avant
garde influence, the emergent materiality,
the anti-gay gaze.
However, again, this is not exclusive
to digital poetry or to e-lit.
Generally.
You notice
this is similar to what happened when
you tried to delimit the region itself.
The more you poked at its boundaries,
the more they seem to dissolve.
The expanded
Latin America had become the world.
Isn't this how you also conclude
in the previous section?
If all digital literature is digital
poetry and Latin
America is the world,
you do the math, dear human reader.
With that,
you conclude that this writing exercise
was probably as good a survey of the main
critical approaches to the concepts
of Latin America digital poetry,
as it was an exploration into the limits
and affordances of writing.
With this
about these topics, with the assistance
and obvious limitations of genAI.
But you also realize
that your focus on frameworks
left, and explore the many and beautiful
works of digital literature
coming from the very broad
and expansive land American region.
What does this say about the limits
of academic discourse and practice?
Why did you do this?
Is your love for these works too big to be
fed into a textual extrusion machine?
Will you break up the model by asking it
the impossible task of reading the poetry
you like?
You have heard of some research
pointing to the single
turn jailbreaking
capabilities of adversarial poetry,
so you never know
better to conclude the chapter
by offering a list of your 20
favorite works
curated by your good human selves.
For reference in this handbook entry.
Many of these works
may not even be considered poetry at all,
but you know they are poetics.
Thank you.
We're going to see some.
That's not what I meant. Thank you.